Register of the Vlastimil Kybal Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Vlastimil Kybal papers,
1913-1968
82004
Kybal, Vlastimil, 1880-1958
29 manuscript boxes (12 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Memoirs, other writings, lectures, notes, correspondence, and printed matter, relating to the history of Czechoslovakia; political, social, and economic conditions in Czechoslovakia, especially during World War II; and political, social, and economic conditions in Latin America.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (30 reels).
Accruals
Increments may have been received since this finding aid was prepared. Please check Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat to find the full extent of the collection.
Biographical Note
1880 May 30 Born, Cernochov u Loun, Czechoslovakia
1899 After graduation from the Gymnasium at Slany, studied history and philosophy at Charles University under the direction of J. Goll, J. Pekar, T. G. Masaryk
1904 Earned a Ph.D. degree in history and philosophy from the Charles University in Prague
1906 Studied in France at the Sorbonne, College de France, Ecole des Hautes Etudes, Ecole de Sciences Politiques, and at the university in Bonn, Germany
1920-1925 Czechoslovak ambassador to Italy
1925-1927 Czechoslovak ambassador to Brazil and Argentina
1927-1933 Czechoslovak ambassador to Spain and Portugal
1935-1939 Czechoslovak ambassador to Mexico and the Central American states
1939-1942 Associate at round-table sessions of the Institute of World Affairs, Riverside, California Lectured on Czechoslovakia at the University of California, Berkeley, the Pacific College, Stockton, and at the University of Southern California in Los Angeles
1944-1948 Research Fellow in History at Yale University Lectured at American universities, in particular Columbia University in New York Contributed significantly to the creation of the Czechoslovak collection of books, serials, and writings at the Library of Congress
1948 Remained in exile in the United States after the February Coup d'etat
1948 October 29 Appointed Consultant on Czechoslovakian Publications for the Yale University Library
1958 January 2 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The Vlastimil Kybal papers were donated to the Hoover Institution Archives by his son, Dalimil Kybal, in 1982, and consist mostly of his speeches and writings.
As a historian, Kybal devoted great attention to Czech history, namely to the analyses of the ideological roots of the Hussite movement, and, in particular, to the personality of Jan Hus himself. In Kybal's writings (see "John Hus," "Husitske dedictvi: Jan Hus a jeho vyznam pro dnesni zapas"), Hus and his conviction that "Truth conquers all!" served as an inspiration and a symbol of courage in the fight of the Czech and Slovak nation against Nazism. Of great importance are, also Kybal's writings on a Moravian educational reformer, Jan Amos Komensky (see "Komensky a nas zapas," "Komensky jako politik"), and his monograph, Karel Havlicek a nase svoboda.
Also of special note in the speeches and writings file is Kybal's monograph, Saint Francis of Assisi, whose spiritual and social message still attracts devotion of many Christians. The book was awarded the Prize of the City of Prague. The English edition was prepared on the basis of a literal translation from the Czech original, and was published in 1954.
As a diplomat, Kybal contributed a great deal, through his numerous speeches and lectures, to the strengthening of cultural and political relations and deeper mutual understanding between Czechoslovakia and Spain, Portugal, Brazil, Argentina, Mexico, and other Latin American countries (see, in the speeches and writings file, "Cultural Relations between Czechoslovakia and the Spanish and Portuguese Speaking Countries," Jizni Amerika: Prehled hospodarsky, obchodni a politicky, "The Changing Social Structure of the Latin-American Countries," "South America's Place in World Economy," "La aportacion cultural y cientifico de los paises checoslovacos a la civilizacion de America," "Checoslovaquia y Mexico"). There are, however, no documents related to Kybal's various ambassadorships.
Also of great importance are Kybal's memoirs (see "Diplomaticke pameti Vlastimila Kybala," and his writings about political, social and economic conditions in Czechoslovakia, before and during World War II (see, in the speeches and writings file, La republica checoslovaca y su formacion como estado democratico, La republica checoslovaca, su formacion politica y administrativa, su potencia economica, "Checoslovaquia: Su opresion y su resurreccion," "K otazce uznani Ceskoslovenska").
In 1939, shortly before the German occupation of Czechoslovakia, Kybal was retired by Hacha's government from the diplomatic service in Mexico, and he moved to Pasadena, California. He took an active part in the liberation movement of his country, delivering a number of lectures and addresses at many California universities, drawing attention of the American public to the grave situation of the German-occupied Czechoslovak nation (see, in the speeches and writings file, "The Moral Forces of the Czech People: A Tentative Survey of Czech History," "The Collapse of the Czechoslovak Republic through the Foreign Intervention," "The Munich Agreement and Its Diplomatic Background," "The Czechoslovak Republic and Its Formation as a Democracy," "El desmembramiento de Checoslovaquia," "The Central European Problem," "The New Economic Order in Central Europe," "Checoslovaquia: Su opresion y su resurreccion").
Along with his son, Milic, he participated in the activities of various organizations designed to promote better knowledge of Slavic countries and their cooperation with the United States during the war, particularly through the Slavic Radio Program, put on by the Slavic Cultural Association, for which he was a regular speaker.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
World War, 1939-1945--Czechoslovakia.; Czechoslovakia.; Czechoslovakia--Foreign relations--Mexico.; Latin America.; Mexico.; Mexico--Foreign relations--Czechoslovakia.; World War, 1939-1945.
Occupations
Diplomats--Czechoslovakia.
Series Description
- Biographical File, 1919-1968. (Box 1)
  Bibliographies, biographical information, chronological record of daily activities, classification system for Kybal's personal library, and personal correspondence, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Correspondence, 1926-1957. (Box 1-4)
  Letters, notes, and telegrams, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- Speeches and Writings, 1913-1957. (Box 5-26)
  Articles, notes, papers, radio broadcast transcripts, reports, speeches and writings, arranged chronologically by title
- Academic Career File, 1943-1944. (Box 27)
  Course material for lectures on Italy and Czech literature and history given at Iowa University, arranged alphabetically by subject
- Slavic Cultural Association, 1942-1943. (Box 27)
  Agreement, correspondence, and transcripts of broadcasts on the Slavic Radio Program, relating to activities of Vlastimil Kybal as a speaker for the SRP, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Subject File, 1914-1957. (Box 28)
  Articles, brochures, clippings, comments, organizational records, programs, proposals, reports, speeches, writings, printed matter, and miscellany, arranged alphabetically by subject
- Printed Matter, 1938-1966. (Box 29)
  Bulletins, clippings, serial issues, and miscellany, relating mainly to Czechoslovakia
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1919-1968 (Box 1)
  - Bibliographies of Kybal's writings (Folder 1: 1)
  - Biographical sketches (Folder 1: 2)
  - Chronological record of daily activities
    - Brazil, 1925-1927 (Folder 1: 3)
    - Mexico, 1935-1939 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Classification system for Kybal's personal library (Folder 1: 5)
  - Personal correspondence (Folder 1: 6)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1926-1957
  - American Czech Association, Inc., 1941 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Associated Students Occidental College, 1939 (Folder 1: 8)
  - California. Race Relations Commission, 1942 (Folder 1: 9)
  - California Institute of Technology, 1939-1942 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Cardenas, Lazaros, General, n.d. (Folder 1: 11)
  - Ceskoslovenske Narodni Sdruzeni (Czechoslovak National Association), 1940 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Ceskoslovensko-Mexicka Asociace (Czechoslovak-Mexican Association), 1941-1942 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Church History, 1941-1942 (Folder 1: 14)
  - Claremont Colleges, 1938-1940 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Columbia University, 1946-1957 (Folder 1: 16)
  - College of the Pacific, Stockton, 1938-1942 (Folder 1: 17)
  - Commonwealth Club, San Francisco, 1941 (Folder 1: 18)
  - Cumnock School, 1939-1942 (Folder 1: 19)
  - Czechoslovak War Relief, 1943 (Folder 1: 20)
  - Czechoslovakia. Konzulat (Puerto Barrios), 1939-1940 (Folder 1: 21)
  - Czechoslovakia. Statni rada (Government-in-exile, London), 1941-1942 (Folder 1: 22)
  - Democratic Party (Calif.). State Central Committee, 1940 (Folder 1: 23)
  - Duke University Library, 1949 (Folder 1: 24)
  - El Salvador. Ministerio de Defensa Nacional, 1939 (Folder 1: 25)
  - Empresa Editora Zig-Zag, S.A., 1939-1942 (Folder 1: 26)
  - Harvard College Library, 1942 (Folder 1: 27)
  - Harvard College Observatory, 1946-1950 (Folder 1: 28)
  - Hofstra College, 1941 (Folder 1: 29)
  - Hollander, Robert, 1938-1939 (Folder 1: 30)
  - Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace. Library, 1950 (Folder 1: 31)
  - Incisa della Rocchetta, Giovanni, 1926-1952 (Folder 1: 32)
  - Inter-American Monthly, 1942 (Folder 1: 33)
  - Journal of Central European Affairs, 1940-1942 (Folder 1: 34)
  - Klecanda, Vladimir, 1941 (Folder 1: 35)
  - Knopf, Alfred, 1941 (Folder 1: 36)
  - Kulturni Krouzek, 1942 (Folder 1: 37)
  - Laurin, Arne, 1940 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Livingston, Porter, 1941-1942 (Folder 2: 2)
  - Los Angeles Optimist Club, 1942 (Folder 2: 3)
  - Markova, Jirina, 1939-1941 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Masaryk Institute, 1944-1949 (Folder 2: 5-6)
  - Masaryk University, 1948 (Folder 2: 7)
  - Masarykova, Alice, 1939-1941 (Folder 2: 8)
  - McCulloch, W. F., 1939 (Folder 2: 9)
  - Mexico. Comision Honorifica Mexicana, 1939 (Folder 2: 10)
  - Mexico. Comision Mexicana de Cooperacion Intelectual, 1941 (Folder 2: 11)
  - Mexico. Consulado (Los Angeles), 1939-1940 (Folder 2: 12)
  - Mexico. Secretaria de Agricultura y Fomento (Jose G. Parres), 1939 (Folder 2: 13)
  - Mount Saint Mary's College, 1940 (Folder 2: 14)
  - Munk, Frank, 1941-1942 (Folder 2: 15)
  - Narodni a Universitni Knihovna v Praze (National University Library in Prague), 1946-1949 (Folder 2: 16)
  - New York Public Library, 1947-1950 (Folder 2: 17)
  - New York University Library, 1947-1949 (Folder 2: 18)
  - New-Yorske Listy, 1941-1942 (Folder 2: 19)
  - Nosek, Vladimir, 1941-1942 (Folder 2: 20)
  - Novotny, Clarence, 1939-1942 (Folder 2: 21)
  - Odlozilik, Otakar, 1942 (Folder 2: 22)
  - Pallares, Eduardo, 1940 (Folder 2: 23)
  - Pasadena (Calif.). Junior College, 1940-1942 (Folder 2: 24)
  - Pimper, Antonin, 1940 (Folder 2: 25)
  - Poland. Konsulat (Los Angeles), 1941 (Folder 2: 26)
  - Polskie Rzadowe Centrum Informacyjne (New York, N.Y.) (Polish Information Center), 1940-1942 (Folder 2: 27)
  - Poverenictvo Informacii a Osvety, 1949 (Folder 2: 28)
  - Prince, L., 1941-1942 (Folder 2: 29)
  - Princeton University Library, 1946-1950 (Folder 2: 30)
  - Prochazkova, Josefa, 1939 (Folder 2: 31)
  - Prosek, C. E., 1940-1942 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Queens University, 1941 (Folder 3: 2)
  - Reed College, 1942 (Folder 3: 3)
  - Richmond, Pavlina, 1943 (Folder 3: 4)
  - Roosevelt, Franklin Delano, 1941 (Folder 3: 5)
  - Roucek, Josef S., n.d. (Folder 3: 6)
  - Sacasa, Juan B., 1940 (Folder 3: 7)
  - San Diego State College, 1942 (Folder 3: 8)
  - San Francisco Chronicle, 1940 (Folder 3: 9)
  - Sarto, Manuel Sanchez, 1939 (Folder 3: 10)
  - Sbor Sokolic, Los Angeles, 1942 (Folder 3: 11)
  - Schwartz, Theo, 1939 (Folder 3: 12)
  - Severance, Elsie, 1940 (Folder 3: 13)
  - Shao Wen Yuan, 1941 (Folder 3: 14)
  - Skala, Vaclav, 1939 (Folder 3: 15)
  - Slavonic Alliance of California, 1940-1942 (Folder 3: 16)
  - Smid, Josef, 1942 (Folder 3: 17)
  - Sociedad Mexicana de Geografia y Estadistica, 1940 (Folder 3: 18)
  - Sokol, Koloman, 1939-1942 (Folder 3: 19)
  - Soviet Union. Posolstvo (United States), 1942 (Folder 3: 20)
  - Spaniel, O., 1942 (Folder 3: 21)
  - Stein, Otto, 1940-1942 (Folder 3: 22)
  - Styskal, L. J., 1941 (Folder 3: 23)
  - Susta, Josef, 1939 (Folder 3: 24)
  - Sutton, I. B., 1939 (Folder 3: 25)
  - Telocvicna Jednota 'Sokolice Los Angeles,' 1941 (Folder 3: 26)
  - Thomas G. Masaryk Society of Los Angeles, 1940-1941 (Folder 3: 27)
  - Toro, Alfonso, 1939 (Folder 3: 28)
  - United Nations. Library, 1948-1949 (Folder 3: 29)
  - United States. Department of State, 1942 (Folder 3: 30)
  - United States. Library of Congress, 1948-1957 (Folder 3: 31-32)
  - Universidad Nacional de Mexico, 1941 (Folder 3: 33)
  - University of California, Berkeley, 1936-1941 (Folder 3: 34)
  - University of California, Los Angeles, 1937-1942 (Folder 3: 35)
  - University of Chicago, 1941-1950 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - University of North Dakota, 1939 (Folder 4: 2)
  - University of Southern California, 1937-1941 (Folder 4: 3)
  - Vassar College Library, 1946 (Folder 4: 4)
  - Vavra, Stephan A., 1941 (Folder 4: 5)
  - Vazquez, Vela, 1939-1942 (Folder 4: 6)
  - Veterans of Foreign Wars of the United States. Los Angeles Post No. 904, 1942 (Folder 4: 7)
  - Veverka, Madilene, 1939-1942 (Folder 4: 8)
  - Vrazova, Vlasta, 1941 (Folder 4: 9)
  - Wallace, William, 1939 (Folder 4: 10)
  - Welles, Sumner, 1941 (Folder 4: 11)
  - Westermann Co., Inc., 1941-1942 (Folder 4: 12)
  - White, Helen C., 1941 (Folder 4: 13)
  - World Peace Foundation, 1946-1947 (Folder 4: 14)
  - Yale University, 1944-1949 (Folder 4: 15)
  - Zaruba, Emma, 1942 (Folder 4: 16)
  - Miscellaneous, 1939-1956 (Folder 4: 17)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1913-1957 (Box 5)
  - General
    - Bibliographies, Narodni a universitni knihovna v Praze (Folder 5: 1-2)
    - Research notes and excerpts from literature (Folder 5: 3-5)
      (in English, Czech, and Spanish)
    - Research notes and excerpts from literature (in English, Czech, and Spanish) (Box-folder 6: 1-7)
    - Untitled and miscellaneous writings (Folder 6: 8)
  - "El acuerdo de Munich y Checoslovaquia," n.d. (Box-folder 7: 1)
    Typescript
  - "La aportacion cultural y cientifico de los paises checoslovacos a la civilizacion de America," n.d. (Folder 7: 2)
  - "Cesta do Mexica," n.d. (Folder 7: 3)
    Typescript (in Czech)
  - "Checoslovaquia y Mexico," n.d. (Folder 7: 4)
  - "Clare of Assisi," n.d. (Folder 7: 5)
  - "El derrumbamiento de Francia," n.d. (Folder 7: 6)
  - "Europe's Next Outlook," n.d. (Folder 7: 7)
  - "Jiri z Podebrad: Cesky statnik," n.d. (Folder 7: 8-9)
    Typescript. Includes research notes (in Czech)
  - "Komensky a nas zapas," n.d. (Folder 7: 10)
  - "Komensky jako politik," n.d. (Folder 7: 11)
  - "Konference Postupimska," n.d. (Folder 7: 12)
  - "Letadlem do Guatemaly," n.d. (Folder 7: 13)
  - Memoirs
    - "Pameti Vlastimila Kybala," n.d. (unpublished?).
      - "Detstvi a jinosstvi," 1880-1899, volume I (Folder 7: 14)
      - "Prazska studia," 1899-1905, volume II (Folder 7: 15-16)
      - "Pariz, Rim a Evropa," 1906-1913, volume III (Box-folder 8: 1-3)
      - "Cinnost za valky a po valce: Rimska mise," 1913-1925", volume IV (Folder 8: 4-5)
      - "Diplomaticka cinnost v Brazilii a Argentine," 1925-1927, volume V (Folder 8: 6)
    - "Diplomaticke pameti Vlastimila Kybala," n.d. (unpublished?). (Box 9)
      - "Diktatura a konec monarchie, 1927-1931, part I (Folder 9: 1)
      - "Putovani po Spanelsku a Portugalsku," 1928-1931, part II (Folder 9: 2)
      - "Prvni leta republiky," 1931-1933, part III (Folder 9: 3)
      - "Mexiko a Stredni Amerika," 1935-1939, part IV (Folder 9: 4-5)
  - "The Minority Problem in Czechoslovakia," n.d. (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - "Nuremberg Trials," n.d. (Folder 10: 2)
  - "President Roosevelt a Cechoslovaci," n.d. (Folder 10: 3)
  - "El problema centro-europeo," n.d. (Folder 10: 4-5)
  - "Las relaciones entre Checoslovaquia y Mexico," n.d. (Folder 10: 6)
  - "La republica czechoslovaca," n.d. (Folder 10: 7)
  - "Restoration of Czechoslovakia as European Necessity," n.d. (Folder 10: 8)
  - Review of John T. Whitaker, Americas to the South, n.d. (Folder 10: 9)
  - "La solucion internacional del problema sudetino," n.d. (Folder 10: 10)
  - Speech, National School of Agriculture, Chapingo, Mexico, n.d. (Folder 10: 11)
    Typescript (in Spanish)
  - Speech on agriculture in Czechoslovakia, n.d. (Folder 10: 12)
  - "The Struggle for Czechoslovakia: A Documentary History 1939-1942 with a Historical Introduction," n.d. (Folder 10: 13-16)
    Typescript (in English and Spanish)
  - "The Struggle for Czechoslovakia: A Documentary History 1939-1942 with a Historical Introduction," n.d. (Box-folder 11: 1-5)
  - "Svaty Vaclav a naciste," n.d. (Box-folder 12: 1)
  - "The Tragedy of Czechoslovakia: A Critical Summary of the Principal Events from March until October 1938," n.d. (Folder 12: 2-3)
  - "Yale University darovala na 1800 knih Prazske universite," n.d. (Folder 12: 4)
  - "Zizka," n.d. (Folder 12: 5)
    Research notes, holograph, and typescript
  - "Zrizeni a cinnost Spojenych narodu," n.d. (Folder 12: 6)
  - Svaty Frantisek z Assisi, Prague, 1913 - American edition (Saint Francis of Assisi, Ave Maria Press, Notre Dame, 1954)
    - Typescript of index (Folder 12: 7)
    - Printed copy (Folder 12: 8)
    - Reviews (Folder 12: 9)
    - Correspondence, including with publisher Ave Maria Press, 1946-1955 (Folder 12: 10-11)
  - La republica checoslovaca, su formacion politica y administrativa, su potencia economica, Madrid, 1933. (Box-folder 13: 1-2)
    Typescript and printed copy
  - "Jizni Amerika ve svetovem hospodarstvi," speech, Prague, 1934 October 22. (Folder 13: 3)
    Printed copy (in Czech)
  - Jizni Amerika: Prehled hospodarsky, obchodni a politicky, Prague, 1935. (Folder 13: 4-5)
    Printed copy (in English and Czech)
  - "Mexiko a Stredni Amerika," lecture, Svobodna skola politickych nauk, Prague, 1935 May. (Folder 13: 6)
  - "Mexiko na prazske veletrhy," 1935 August 1. (Folder 13: 7)
  - "Hospodarska situace v Mexiku," 1935 October 1. (Folder 13: 8)
  - "Obchodovani s Mexikem," 1935 November 25. (Folder 13: 9)
  - "El intercambio comercial entre Checoslovaquia y Mexico, 1935 December. (Folder 13: 10)
  - "Nac stune nas export," 1935 December 1. (Folder 13: 11)
  - "Z cest po Mexiku," 1935 December 2. (Folder 13: 12)
  - "Papirove exportovani," 1935 December 15. (Folder 13: 13)
  - "Viaje diplomatico por el Mexico de hoy, 1935 December 21. (Folder 13: 14)
  - "Co lze ocekavat od Exportniho ustavu v zamori," 1935 December 29. (Folder 13: 15)
  - "Co nam chybi v cizine," 1936. (Folder 13: 16)
  - "Jak se americane chovaji ke svym sousedum," 1936. (Folder 13: 17)
  - "La educacion fisica en Checoslovaquia," 1936 March 2. (Folder 13: 18)
  - "Masaryk como Presidente de la Republica," 1936 March 6. (Folder 13: 19)
  - "La republica checoslovaca desde el punto de vista historico, politico y economico," speech, Universidad Nacional, San Salvador, 1936 April 30. (Folder 13: 20)
  - "Co skrti nas vyvoz," 1936 May 29. (Folder 13: 21)
  - "Hospodarska obnova v Americe," 1936 June 23. (Folder 13: 22)
  - "Mexiko na prazske veletrhy," 1936 August 1. (Folder 13: 23)
  - Speech, Primera Asamblea Infantil Antialcoholica, Mexico, 1936 September 27. (Folder 13: 24)
  - "Hlas Ameriky," 1936 December 2. (Folder 13: 25)
  - "El 87th aniversario del presidente Tomas G. Masaryk," radio address, 1937 March 7. (Folder 13: 26)
  - "La republica checoslovaca en su ultimo ano y sys relaciones con la republica mexicana," 1937 October 24. (Folder 13: 27)
  - "Political and Economic Development of Czechoslovakia," 1938? (Folder 13: 28)
  - Checoslovaquia y Alemania, Mexico, 1938. (Box-folder 14: 1)
    Printed copy (in Spanish)
  - La republica checoslovaca y su formacion como estado democratico, 1938. (Folder 14: 2)
    Printed copy
  - "No existe un peligro checo," 1938 July 19. (Folder 14: 3)
  - "La calumniosa propaganda nazista," 1938 August 26. (Folder 14: 4)
  - Lecture tour in California, 1938 September. (Folder 14: 5)
    Correspondence and clippings
  - "El problema checoslovaco y su solucion," lecture, California, 1938 September. (Folder 14: 6)
  - "El problema minoritario en Checoslovaquia," lecture, California, 1938 September. (Folder 14: 7)
  - Speech, the International Anti-War Congress, Mexico, 1938 September 10. (Folder 14: 8)
  - Speech, Sokol, San Francisco, 1938 September 19. (Folder 14: 9)
  - "Czechoslovakia's Position among the Nations," lecture, Berkeley, California, 1938 September 20. (Folder 14: 10)
  - "Checoslovaquia fue victima de la politica imperialista," 1938 October 6. (Folder 14: 11)
  - Speech, Chihuahua, Mexico, 1938 October 6. (Folder 14: 12)
  - Speech, Mexico, 1938 October 12. (Folder 14: 13)
  - Speech commemorating Czechoslovak independence, Palacio de Bellas Artes, Mexico, 1938 October 28. (Folder 14: 14)
  - "Conmemoracion de la independencia checoslovaca," 1938 October 30. (Folder 14: 15)
  - "La estructura economica de la actual Checoslovaquia," 1938 November 11. (Folder 14: 16)
  - "Nase slabost v cizine," 1938 November 12. (Folder 14: 17)
  - "El caso checoslovaco," 1938 December 3. (Folder 14: 18)
  - "Falsedades sobre Checoslovaquia," 1938 December 3. (Folder 14: 19)
  - "Que es Checoslovaquia?" 1938 December 4. (Folder 14: 20)
  - "Nase prace v Mexiku a stredni Americe: 1935-1938," 1939 January. (Folder 15: 1)
  - "Cargos al Doctor Benes," 1939 January 8. (Folder 15: 2)
  - Letter to the editor, Zlin, 1939 January 25. (Folder 15: 3)
  - "The Economic Structure of Present-Day Czechoslovakia," World Affairs Interpreter, 1939 Spring. (Folder 15: 4)
  - Speech on the German occupation of Czechoslovakia, Claremont College, California, 1939 March 21. (Folder 15: 5)
  - "The English Intervention in Central European Affairs," Athenaeum, Pasadena, California, 1939 April 13. (Folder 15: 6)
  - "The Defense of the Czech Nation," speech, Pasadena Junior College, California, 1939 April 25. (Folder 15: 7)
    Holograph and typescript
  - "The Moral Forces of the Czech People: A Tentative Survey of Czech History," lecture, Claremont College, California, 1939 April 28. (Folder 15: 8)
  - "The Collapse of the Czechoslovak Republic through the Foreign Intervention," lecture, Claremont College, 1939 May 2. (Folder 15: 9)
  - "The Foundation and Work of Masaryk's Republic," lecture, Claremont College, 1939 May 2. (Folder 15: 10)
  - "Decisive Hour for Poland," 1939 June 27. (Folder 15: 11)
  - "The Munich Agreement and Its Diplomatic Background," University of California, Berkeley, 1939 July 13. (Folder 15: 12)
  - "The Czechoslovak Republic and Its Formation as a Democracy," lecture, University of Southern California, 1939 August 15. (Folder 15: 13)
  - Speech, Mexican colony in Pasadena, California, 1939 August 24. (Folder 15: 14)
  - "South America's Place in World Economy," 1939 August 29. (Folder 15: 15)
  - "El desmembramiento de Checoslovaquia," 1939 October. (Folder 15: 16)
  - "The European War as a Diplomatic Struggle between the Greater Germany and Western Europe," A Town Meeting on the Second World War, California Institute of Technology, 1939 November 7. (Folder 15: 17)
  - "History of Central Europe," lecture, Mayfield School, Pasadena, California, 1939 November 25. (Box-folder 16: 1-2)